Guide to the Jon Weiner Papers regarding Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. Sears Roebuck WAG.050
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jon Weiner Papers regarding Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. Sears Roebuck
1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weiner, Jon
WAG.050
1 Linear Feet 1 box
Historical/Biographical Note
In 1979 the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission filed an anti-discrimination action against Sears Roebuck & Company. The complaint covered patterns of sex discrimination between 1973 and 1980. It was the last of the major corporate sex bias cases to be litigated by the Commission, and the only one to not be settled out of court.
Central to Sears' arguments was the expert testimony of Rosalind Rosenberg, a professor of history at Barnard College, and a writer in women's studies. To counter her statements that women didn't want the high-commission sales jobs that were at issue in the case, the EEOC called on Alice Kessler-Harris, a professor of history at Hofstra University, and the author of several books and articles on women's work. Their opposing testimonies reached beyond the courtroom, stirring a vigorous debate throughout the labor history and women's history disciplines, and promoting extensive discourses in academic journals as well as panels at historians' conferences.
A judgment on the case was handed down by District Court Judge John Norberg in January, 1986-a decisive victory for Sears Roebuck.
Scope and Contents
The documents in this collection are the research files of Jon Weiner who wrote The Nation article "Women's History on Trial," September 7, 1985. Aside from a few press clippings 1984-1986, all the documents in this collection are legal records of the EEOC v. Sears case from 1985-1986, when the controversy between historians Rosalind Rosenberg and Alice Kessler-Harris came to the force of the trial.
Included in the collection are trial transcripts, depositions, briefs, and Judge Norberg's opinion and order as well as Sears' extensive billing for the costs of the case. These records constitute only one linear foot and so are arranged in the approximate chronological order as they were received from the donor, Jon Weiner.
The collection is remarkable not only for its documentation of the court proceedings on this landmark case, but also for the expert testimonies of the two historian witnesses. Each provides a valuable historical discussion on the nature of women's work and employment opportunity, and each is carefully argued and thoroughly documented.
This collection is important for researchers into the history of equal employment opportunity as well as for more general readers of women's history. The Rosenberg/Kessler-Harris debate constitutes a significant delineation of theories on working women, and reviews the history of women's work in the USA. It probes patterns of corporate sex bias as well as legitimate corporate programs for equal opportunity. Finally, because the historians' opposition generated such a lively controversy within the discipline, there is some basic material here on the uses of historical research in public policy.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These records were donated to the Tamiment Library by Jon Weiner in July 1986. The accession number associated with this gift is 1986.043.
Weiner, Jon
- Miscellaneous clippings, includes September 7, 1985 The Nation article by Jon Weiner, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Written testimonies of Rosalind Rosenberg and Alice Kessler-Harris, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Rosalind Rosenberg deposition, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Rosalind Rosenberg trial transcript, April 11, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Sears trial brief, September/October 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Kessler-Harris trial transcript, June 6-June 7, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Rosenberg surrebuttal, June 22, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous trial testimony, April/May 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Closing arguments, June 28, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Equal Employment Opportunity Commission final brief, June 26, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Sears post-trial brief, June 26, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Judge John A. Nordberg, opinion and order, January 31, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Sears petition for fees, February 11, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Sears bill of costs, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Equal Employment Opportunity Commission opposition on fees, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
- Sears reply on fees, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Addendum transcipt of court case, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)